# G. William Chapman IV

website: https://wchapman.github.io/

### Summary

Upcoming PhD graduate in computational neuroscience, with an additional 6 years as a software developer and scientific analyst in research-oriented settings. As a scientific analyst I have specialized in temporally-aware analysis, with a strong emphasis on interacting with subject-experts. As an independent researcher, I have focused on novel neural network architectures to support temporal prediction, spatial navigation, and symbolic reasoning.

#### EDUCATION

Boston University
Doctor of Philosophy - Computational Neuroscience
December

December 2022 (expected)

Email: g.william.chapman.iv@gmail.com

University of Colorado

Boulder, CO

Master of Arts - Cognitive Psychology

2018

Boston University

Boston, MA

Boston, MA

Bachelor of Science - Biomedical Engineering, Minor in Electrical Engineering

2012

SKILLS

• Languages: Python, MATLAB, R, Bash, SQL, LATEX

• Frameworks: Scikit Learn, PyTorch, Pandas, Numpy, Slurm, SGE, Git

• General: Machine Learning, Time Series, Advanced Statistical Analysis, Dynamical Systems, Biomedical Engineering, Project Management, Scientific & Data Communication

# EXPERIENCE

# **Boston University**

Boston, MA

Graduate Research Fellow

2018 - Present

- Biological Predictive Coding: Created a novel, biologically inspired, machine learning architecture and learning rule for temporal prediction. Functions above state-of-the-art for both short-term and long-term sequence generation, with applications for lifelong learning, and generalization.
- **Egocentric-Allocentric Transformations**: Designed an explainable ML model which receives self-centered sensor and motor information, fusing sensor information through recurrent hidden layers. Hidden layers create explicit reference-frame transformations, in addition to low-dimensional latent representations.
- Symbolic Predictive Learning: Created a novel architecture which utilizes predictive coding and dynamic attentional routing to solve a symbolic reasoning task.

#### eCortex & University of Colorado

Boulder, CO

Neural Modeler

2016 - 2018

- **Symbolic Reasoning**: Extended existing computational models of working memory to create a model capable of simple symbolic processing, utilizing attentional mechanisms.
- **Electrophysiology**: Designed and ran a corresponding EEG experiment to test model predictions. Created novel causal frequency-time analyses to determine timecourse of functional connectivity.

# Center for Systems Neuroscience

Boston, MA

Research Software Engineer

May 2012 - August 2016

- Software Design: Primary contributor for centralized MATLAB-based OOP software for standardized data storage and exploratory analyses of neural and behavioral data across multiple labs.
- Data Pipelines: Created standardized data pipelines for preprocessing various unstructured data and combining into a centralized SQL database, automated by cloud-computing tasks.
- Research: Primary statistical analysis expert for over ten peer-reviewed publications in systems and computational neuroscience, including time-series analysis, frequentist statistics, generalized linear models, and data visualization.

#### **Boston Medical Center**

Boston, MA

Neuroimaging Research Assistant

May 2009 - May 2012

• Alzheimer's Disease: Primary individual for data pipelines and novel analysis of structural MRI and behavioral data, leading to predictive models of clinical Alzheimer's Disease progression.

- 1. A. S. Alexander, J. C. Tung, G. W. Chapman, A. M. Conner, L. E. Shelley, M. E. Hasselmo, and D. A. Nitz, "Adaptive integration of self-motion and goals in posterior parietal cortex," *Cell Reports*, vol. 38, p. 110504, Mar. 2022
- 2. L. C. Carstensen, A. S. Alexander, G. W. Chapman, A. J. Lee, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Neural responses in retrosplenial cortex associated with environmental alterations," *iScience*, vol. 24, p. 103377, Nov. 2021
- 3. M. E. Hasselmo, A. S. Alexander, A. Hoyland, J. C. Robinson, M. J. Bezaire, G. W. Chapman, A. Saudargiene, L. C. Carstensen, and H. Dannenberg, "The unexplored territory of neural models: Potential guides for exploring the function of metabotropic neuromodulation," *Neuroscience*, p. S0306452220302141, Apr. 2020
- 4. A. S. Alexander, J. C. Robinson, H. Dannenberg, N. R. Kinsky, S. J. Levy, W. Mau, G. W. Chapman, D. W. Sullivan, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Neurophysiological coding of space and time in the hippocampus, entorhinal cortex, and retrosplenial cortex," *Brain and Neuroscience Advances*, vol. 4, p. 239821282097287, Jan. 2020
- 5. A. S. Alexander, L. C. Carstensen, J. R. Hinman, F. Raudies, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Egocentric boundary vector tuning of the retrosplenial cortex," *Science Advances*, July 2019
- 6. J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Neuronal representation of environmental boundaries in egocentric coordinates," *Nature Communications*, vol. 10, p. 2772, Dec. 2019
- 7. C. K. Monaghan, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Systemic administration of two different anxiolytic drugs decreases local field potential theta frequency in the medial entorhinal cortex without affecting grid cell firing fields," *Neuroscience*, vol. 364, pp. 60–70, 2017
- 8. J. R. Hinman, M. P. Brandon, J. R. Climer, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Multiple Running Speed Signals in Medial Entorhinal Cortex," *Neuron*, vol. 91, no. 3, pp. 666–679, 2016
- 9. M. Ferrante, C. F. Shay, Y. Tsuno, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Post-Inhibitory Rebound Spikes in Rat Medial Entorhinal Layer II/III Principal Cells: In-Vivo, In-Vitro, and Computational Modeling Characterization," *Cerebral Cortex*, no. March, 2016
- 10. Y. Tsuno, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Rebound spiking properties of mouse medial entorhinal cortex neurons in vivo.," *The European journal of neuroscience*, vol. 42, pp. 2974–2984, Jan. 2015
- 11. C. F. Shay, M. Ferrante, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Rebound spiking in layer II medial entorhinal cortex stellate cells: Possible mechanism of grid cell function," *Neurobiology of Learning and Memory*, 2015
- 12. F. Raudies, M. P. Brandon, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Head direction is coded more strongly than movement direction in a population of entorhinal neurons," *Brain Research*, vol. 1621, pp. 355–367, Sept. 2015
- 13. A. L. Jefferson, K. A. Gifford, S. Damon, G. W. Chapman, D. Liu, J. Sparling, V. Dobromyslin, and D. Salat, "Gray & white matter tissue contrast differentiates Mild Cognitive Impairment converters from non-converters," *Brain Imaging and Behavior*, vol. 9, pp. 141–148, June 2015
- 14. K. a. Gifford, D. Liu, S. M. Damon, G. W. Chapman, R. R. Romano, L. R. Samuels, Z. Lu, and A. L. Jefferson, "Subjective Memory Complaint Only Relates to Verbal Episodic Memory Performance in Mild Cognitive Impairment," *Journal of Alzheimer's Disease*, vol. 44, pp. 309–318, Jan. 2015

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Boston University

Boston, MA

Graduate Teaching Fellow

2018 - 2020

- Cognitive Neuroscience & Learning and Memory: Led weekly discussion groups, reviewing and previewing material; created exams.
- University of Colorado

Boulder, CO

Graduate Teaching Fellow

2016 - 2018

• Advanced Cognitive Neuroscience & Research Methods: Independently designed lab section for both courses, leading students through a semester-long experiential learning in R (programming language), leading to a capstone project for each group.

Boston University

Boston, MA 2011-2012

Teaching Assistant

• Biomedical Instrumentation I & II: Led three sections of laboratory in each semester, guiding students in experiments based on control theory and signal processing.

# Professional Service

- Invited reviewer: Neural Networks (2018-present); Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) (2019-present); International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) (2020-present)
- Academic Planning Committee: Graduate Student representative on a small panel of faculty responsible for overseeing and approving changes in undergraduate and graduate degree program requirements. 2018 2019.

- 1. G. W. Chapman, "Egocentric Signals to Allocentric Maps, and Back Again," May 2022
- 2. G. W. Chapman and M. E. Hasselmo, "Trajectory prediction in a biologically inspired network with a strong inductive bias," Oct. 2020
- 3. G. W. Chapman and M. E. Hasselmo, "Trajectory prediction in a biologically inspired network," Nov. 2020
- 4. G. W. Chapman, "A model of relational reasoning through selective attention and working memory," Mar. 2019
- 5. L. C. Carstensen, A. Alexander, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Representations of landmarks in the retrosplenial cortex," Oct. 2019
- 6. A. Alexander, L. C. Carstensen, G. W. Chapman, F. Raudies, J. R. Hinman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Egocentric boundary vector tuning of the retrosplenial cortex," Oct. 2019
- 7. J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Neuronal representation of egocentric boundaries in egocentric coordinates," Oct. 2018
- 8. J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Egocentric representation of environmental boundaries in the striatum," June 2018
- 9. L. C. Carstensen, A. Alexander, J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Spatial correlates of the retrosplenial cortex during free exploration," Oct. 2018
- A. Alexander, L. C. Carstensen, F. Raudies, G. W. Chapman, J. R. Hinman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Retrosplenial and entorhinal cortical representations during visually-based triangulation," Oct. 2018
- 11. J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Egocentric representation of environmental boundaries in the striatum," Oct. 2017
- 12. J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Representation of environmental boundaries within an egocentric reference frame," Oct. 2016
- 13. Y. Tsuno, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "In Vivo rebound spike characteristics of medial entorhinal cortex cells," Oct. 2015
- 14. C. K. Monaghan, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Medial Septal infusion of a serotonin 1A agonist anxiolytic reduces theta frequency in the medial entorhinal cortex," Oct. 2015
- 15. J. R. Hinman, J. R. Climer, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "A novel slow oscillatory neuron in the lateral septum," Oct. 2015
- 16. C. F. Shay, M. Ferrante, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Layer II Medial Entorhinal Cortex Stellate cells in rat display phase specific post inhibitory rebound spiking," Nov. 2014
- 17. M. Ferrante, C. F. Shay, Y. Tsuno, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Modeling Intrinsic and Extrinsic mechanisms in rat entorhinal cortex and hippocampus that may influence grid and place cells," Nov. 2014
- 18. J. R. Climer, R. DiTullio, J. R. Hinman, G. W. Chapman, M. P. Brandon, M. E. Hasselmo, and U. T. Eden, "Addressing Theta rhythmicity in extracellularly recorded neurons in rat and bat," Oct. 2014
- 19. F. Raudies, M. P. Brandon, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Movement Direction is Not Coded by the Firing of Most Entorhinal Cells, but Required by Grid Cell Models," Oct. 2013
- 20. J. R. Hinman, M. P. Brandon, G. W. Chapman, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Speed Modulation of Medial Entorhinal Cortical Neurons During Medial Septal Inactivation," Oct. 2013
- 21. K. A. Gifford, S. Damon, R. R. Romano, G. W. Chapman, and A. L. Jefferson, "Cognitive Complaints are related to memory performance in older adults with Mild Cognitive Impairment," Feb. 2013
- 22. M. Ferrante, C. F. Shay, G. W. Chapman, M. Migliore, N. J. Kopell, H. Eichenbaum, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Modeling Intrinsic and Extrinsic Mechanisms in Rat Entorhinal Cortex and Hippocampus that May Influence firing of grid and place cells," Oct. 2013
- 23. G. W. Chapman, N. W. Schultheiss, M. P. Brandon, and M. E. Hasselmo, "Theta Cycle Skipping Relationships in the Medial Entorhinal Cortex are Robust," Oct. 2013
- 24. A. L. Jefferson, G. W. Chapman, J. Sparling, K. A. Gifford, B. Martin, V. Dobromyslin, and D. Salat, "Semi-automated Method for Quantifying Infarcts in Older Adults with and without Dementia," Feb. 2012
- 25. G. W. Chapman, A. L. Jefferson, K. A. Gifford, J. Sparling, N. Cantwell, R. R. Romano, V. Dobromyslin, and D. Salat, "Grey-White Matter Contrast Ratio Relates to Progression in Mild Cognitive Impairment.," July 2012

- 26. G. W. Chapman, A. Gentile, N. Cantwell, V. Williams, D. Salat, and A. L. Jefferson, "White Matter Integrity in Entorhinal Cortex & Parahippocampal Region is Associated with Memory Performances in Individuals with Mild Cognitive Impairment.," Feb. 2010
- 27. M. Badaracco, K. A. Gifford, A. Gentile, G. W. Chapman, Y. Tripodis, and A. L. Jefferson, "The Relation of Hypertension to Cognition in Observational Studies: A Meta-Analysis," Feb. 2010